<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Rome, Spalato's doome. O An epitome of the life and behaviour of M. Antonius de Dominis first Bishop of Segnia, afterwards Archbishop of Spalato; who about some seven or eight yeeres since came from Venice into England: and from thence by the practise and perswasion of the L. Gundamar, departed to Rome: and of late was imprisoned in the catle of Saint Angelo. Herein contained the reasons for which he was imprisoned, together with his miserable disastrous end.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20607</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855648</idno>
  <idno type="VID">21149</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501104</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 7006.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S120451</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99855648e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20607)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21149)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 738:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Rome, Spalato's doome. O An epitome of the life and behaviour of M. Antonius de Dominis first Bishop of Segnia, afterwards Archbishop of Spalato; who about some seven or eight yeeres since came from Venice into England: and from thence by the practise and perswasion of the L. Gundamar, departed to Rome: and of late was imprisoned in the catle of Saint Angelo. Herein contained the reasons for which he was imprisoned, together with his miserable disastrous end.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for Richard Whitaker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: T.H.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 7007a on UMI microfilm, reel 738.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21149:1"/>
            <p>NEWS FROM ROME, Spalato's Doome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or</hi> AN EPITOME OF THE life and behaviour of M. ANTONIUS <hi>de Dominis,</hi> first Bishop of <hi>Segnia,</hi> afterwards Archbishop of <hi>Spalato;</hi> who about some seven or eight yeeres since came from <hi>Venice</hi> into <hi>England:</hi> and from thence by the practise and perswasion of the L. <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damar,</hi> departed to <hi>Rome:</hi> And of late was imprisoned in the Castle of Saint <hi>Angelo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HEREIN IS CONTAINED THE Reasons for which he was imprisoned, together with his miserable disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous <hi>end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Haviland</hi> for RICHARD WHITAKER. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21149:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21149:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN</hi> discreet <hi>Reader,</hi> by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the <hi>Dalmatian Bishop</hi> thus impartially painted out in his colours, thou maist perceive how easie a thing it is, for any man of the meanest capacitie to build ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wind-mills and castles in the aire alone with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: and how dangerous and uncertaine to trust un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable <hi>Rome: Crudelis mater magis, an puer improbus ille?</hi> I can hardly conjecture which may be the more observeable, the Crueltie of mother <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Impiety of her prodigall retired sonne. But I conclude, <hi>Improbus ille puer, crudelis tu quo{que} mater,</hi> Both a wicked son, and an adulterous mother. Yet (Lady <hi>Rome</hi>) let me here dispute the point, whether or no he died thy son: sure I am that since his returne unto thee, he did never totally adhere to thy Religion; but as it shall plainly appeare, did much dislike both thy doctrine and discipline: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise thou wouldest not have used him as a fagot for the fire, but have preserved him rather as a substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Rafter for thy decayed building. But I must needs say, thy mercy is meere crueltie, and thy pietie no lesse than barbarous immanitie. The <hi>Iscocchi</hi> sent forth threats against their <hi>quondam</hi> Bishop, (I
<pb facs="tcp:21149:3"/>meane this same <hi>Dalmatian</hi> Bishop, <hi>M. ANTON. de Dominis</hi>) that if they could lay hands on him, they would make a bag of his skin (as they are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to make of swines skins for wine and oyle in those countries.) It seemes the <hi>Pope</hi> and his shave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or chapmen, could make no use at all of him, but returne him to his Ashes, as they doe all Heretikes, whose cinders they use to sprinkle in the aire, with these words, <hi>Colligat Deus,</hi> Let their God gather them, if he will have them. Mee thinkes they might better have kept him as a Stale to publish more books in his name, or have sent him an Apostle to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> for the conversion of Infidels, whither he would rather have beene packing, than stay at home in <hi>Rome,</hi> there to be sacrificed to their flaming <hi>Aetna,</hi> or be broiling upon the hot coles. <hi>Caveat alter,</hi> Take heed <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Preston,</hi> let not the <hi>Ignatians</hi> prevaile with you to carry a letter to <hi>Rome,</hi> lest you dip your finger in the same sauce. I have heard you may have a Bishopricke in <hi>Rome</hi> for the fetching: So had <hi>Spalato,</hi> procured by the <hi>Spanish Fistulado.</hi> But beside the Castle of <hi>S. Angelo,</hi> he could never reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of his hoped revenewes appendant to his said Promotion. Well, the old Schoole verse shall end all that I intend to perswade in this preluding Preface, <hi>Foelix quem faciunt,</hi> &amp;c. Happie he whom others harmes make to beware.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21149:3"/>
            <head>Nevves from Rome, SPALATO's Doome.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shewing how</hi> M. ANTONIVS de Dominis, <hi>Arch-bishop of</hi> Spalato, <hi>arrived in</hi> England, Anno Dom. 1616. <hi>and of the large protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he made of his Conversion to the true and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ectumest Index sui &amp; obliqui:</hi> True levell laid to a crooked worke, discovereth what is out of order. The old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe saith, It is good to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the lame Post, and the last newes are ever truest. We ought not to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve every spirit,</hi> but the <hi>spirits</hi> must be <hi>tried,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>S. Iohn.</hi> For Truth is the daughter of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21149:4"/>Time. It cannot bee denied but that <hi>England</hi> hath beene gulled by a <hi>Dalmatian Bishop,</hi> whom time hath discovered to be the only <hi>Ecebolius</hi> of our daies, unsavourie salt, a man of no Religion, a Run-away from the Truth.</p>
               <p>He came from <hi>Venice</hi> (where hee had made some time of abode) into <hi>England, Anno</hi> 1616. where being arrived, hee pretended hee was sent from God to judge, to reforme, and to reunite the Christian world. He likened himselfe to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> in leaving at the voice of God his house, his parentage, and his countrey. He familiarly compared himselfe with <hi>S. Paul,</hi> in his former zeale against the true Religion, as he said, in the manner of his Conversion miraculously effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, in receiving his Gospell, as he would have it seeme, not from man, but immediatly from God, in being an universall Apostle, as hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and sent unto all Nations: and lastly, in that high degree of <hi>Love,</hi> whereby he offered himselfe to bee made an <hi>Anathema</hi> for his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. By tongue and pen, by word and writing upon his afore-said arrivall, he expressed all these Characters of a miraculous inspired Convert. But this Mountebanke in fine proved as a gilded pill composed of these two Ingredients, <hi>Dishone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty</hi> and <hi>Dissimulation.</hi> The <hi>Herodians,</hi> and <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21149:4"/>servants came to Christ with many fawning insinuations, telling him that he was the plaine truth, that he taught the way of God truly, that hee regarded no mans person, when as indeed their thoughts were otherwise, their purpose was to intangle him in their words, that they might catch advātage against him, &amp; so cut his throat. This aforesaid <hi>Dalmatian Bishop</hi> came into our kingdome with infinite protestations of sincere dealing, confessing that our Religion was the Truth and none other; professing that our Church of <hi>England</hi> was the most <hi>Orthodox</hi> and true Church in the world. But (saith <hi>Salomon) as if thou wouldest adorne an earthen vessell with drossie silver,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.23.</note>
                  <hi>so were his swelling lips joyned with a most wicked heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To bee the better welcome into our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he bedecked himselfe with the partie-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured feathers of all other Moderne Religions: yet before his departure, some worthy and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men of our Church well observing his pide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat, having pluckt him like <hi>Aesops</hi> Crow, shewed him to be naked without any Religion at all; apt enough, upon occasion, to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised and deny Christ Iesus. Yet I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l not here passe by certaine <hi>Dispositions</hi> of his, which hee saith prepared his minde to the change of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21149:5"/>Religion, and to become a Protestant. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the <hi>Reasons</hi> which hee laid downe, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him to a stedfast imbracing of the said Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Certaine dispositions that prepared the Arch-bishop of</hi> Spalato <hi>his minde, and strong reasons that moved him (as he protested upon his comming over into</hi> England) <hi>to become a Protestant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>FOr the better unmasking of this egregious Hypocrite, and (as he after proved) impious Apostate, I will not omit those particulars, which he set downe with his owne hand, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioning his comming into this kingdome, and his change of Religion.</p>
               <p>Somewhat a farre off (as he said) disposed his minde: As first, that from a Boy, hee was much troubled with a vehement suspition that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doctrine was not true, which suspition he ever resisted.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this suspition was much increased in him, because hee saw that neither Students were permitted to reade such Writers, as were contrarie to the doctrine of <hi>Rome</hi> (being infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21149:5"/>to beleeve, that the opinions of those Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were truly delivered unto them by their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters) nor such as had heard their Divinitie, and were preferred to Ecclesiasticall dignitie, could be allowed to reade any such Authors.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he saith, that from the first yeere of his clergie, he had nourished in himselfe an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> desire of the union of all Christian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, inquiring what might be the cause of their Schisme, which did excruciate and torment his minde, and did still consume and waste him with such griefe and sorrow as was wonderfull.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that being made a Bishop, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reade bookes of printed Sermons, <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragesimals,</hi> and others, for the exercise of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopall function in preaching, he found great abuse of Scripture in them, Apocryphall and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous examples, Inventions of Avarice and Ambition, not without superstition, wherewith the people were deluded.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, that in reading the Fathers, he observed that his Masters had taught him many things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, and that the Ecclesiasticall disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> did differ verie much from the ancient practise thereof.</p>
               <p>These considerations he called Dispositions, which somewhat prepared his minde (as well
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21149:6"/>they might) to make mutation of Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause (as he said) they made him to see a farre off, all was not well with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> It followeth to consider what (he said) moved him directly to leave the abomination of the Romish religion.</p>
               <p>He saith, that of a Bishop, being made an Archbishop, two accidents fell out that compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to studie these matters more earnestly and eagerly than before he did, and made him turne over more than once or twice the Fathers, the Canons, the Councels, and ancient Records of the Catholike Church.</p>
               <p>The first was, that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> and his Suffragan Bishops that were under him, began to perturbe his Metropolitane rights.</p>
               <p>The second, that after the <hi>Interdict</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> there came books from <hi>Rome,</hi> strangely taxing the Bishops of the <hi>Venetian</hi> state who did not obey.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Bishops now adaies under the Pope have but the name of Bishops, all their Iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is taken from them, and are subject not only to the Pope, but also to Cardinals, Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Legates, Inquisitors, and innumerable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Religious men, who now have greater faculties than Bishops, and drowne their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21149:6"/>
               <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Pope</hi> is now a <hi>temporall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> and the Church is become a Vineyard, to make him drunke, and a flocke to feed him with her owne bloud.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, his eyes being opened, he saw easily, plainly and perfectly, that the Churches whom Rome had made her enemies, did differ little or nothing from the pure doctrine of the ancient Church.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, in <hi>Rome</hi> are coined every day innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Articles of faith, without any foundation, with extreme violence.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>Rome</hi> hath puld out the eyes of the Church of Christ by suppressing the sacred <hi>Councels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eightly, the <hi>Catholike</hi> Church is now confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be made the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninthly, in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nay in the <hi>Pope</hi> alone, the whole spirit of Christ, promised to the Catholike Church, is beleeved to reside.</p>
               <p>Lastly, whatsoever hath beene spoken hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in honour of the universall Church, is now most wrongfully inforced upon the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> alone, whereof it followeth, that the soules of men being thereby miserably deceived and blinded, they fall together with their blinde guides into the pit of perdition.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21149:7"/>
               <p>The aforesaid <hi>Motives</hi> were forcible enough to have drawne his feet out of the mire of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonish</hi> error, and to set him in the right path and way of godlinesse. And he began well to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereof: Who hindered him that he did not persevere? <hi>Praestat nunquam incepisse quam turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in medio defecisse:</hi> It had beene better indeed he had never come from the fen of <hi>Rome,</hi> than to have returned as he did with the <hi>dog</hi> to his former <hi>vomit,</hi> and with the <hi>Sow</hi> to the <hi>wallowing in the mire.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. lib. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ita beata.</note>
                  <hi>Multi usque ad virtutis ianua perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nêre &amp; redeunt, nec domum virtutis intrant: Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt sed non perficiunt, sicut Moses qui terram san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam è monte Nebonate viderunt, sed non intrarunt▪</hi> Many (saith <hi>S. Augustine</hi>) have come as farre as the doore of Vertue, and yet forthwith become retrograde: Many like <hi>Moses</hi> see the holy Land a farre off from the Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> but wil not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; they had rather (as <hi>Spalato</hi> did) to returne to the flesh-pots of Aegypt, than to remaine in a land of peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21149:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Containing the life and behaviour of the said Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of</hi> Spalato <hi>whilest he remained in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe <hi>Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Spalato</hi> having after his comming into <hi>England</hi> by the aforesaid pretended <hi>dispositions</hi> and <hi>motives</hi> made verball profession of his true Conversion, it pleased our most gratious Soveraigne, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable patterne and patron of piety and religion, to advance him to such Ecclesiasticall dignitie in our Church, that his Adversaries might have no cause to scoffe at his low deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted estate, or himselfe discouraged for want of competencie to maintaine his continued Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Hee had therefore conferred on him the <hi>Mastership</hi> of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> the <hi>Deanrie</hi> of <hi>Winsor,</hi> and the Parsonage of <hi>West-Ilslye</hi> in <hi>Barkshire;</hi> The two former places of great honour and credit, and the latter of no lesse benefit. The worst of the three too good for this undeser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mountebank; who hath since proclaimed himselfe unto the world a <hi>knave in graine,</hi> a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21149:8"/>man of cauterized conscience, prostituted hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and meretricious impudencie.</p>
               <p>As for some turpitude of his (when he lived here, which was kept a while very covert) I had rather it should be buried still, than desile my pen, my selfe, and the world with the discoverie of it, except I should be inforced to it. For alas, the the judgement of God hath overtaken him, and that which he feared is come upon him. Yet I will indite him as guilty of these foure: An <hi>arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Impostor;</hi> an <hi>irreligious Sycophant;</hi> a <hi>luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous glutton;</hi> a <hi>perjurd Apostate. Pride</hi> being linkt with <hi>Imposture, Irreligion</hi> with <hi>Slander, Lechery</hi> with <hi>Gluttony,</hi> and <hi>Periurie</hi> with <hi>Apostasie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And first I arraigne him for an arrogant Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postor, guilty of palpable lying, which was the very foame of his Pride and Arrogancie. For proofe of his lying, I alleage these particulars.</p>
               <p>He became indebted to us, upon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming over, ten great Volumes to be written by himselfe against the Romanists; yet he missed his time of payment, and hath since proved plaine bankrupt. He boasted that the revenues of his <hi>Dalmatian Bishopricke</hi> amounted to the value of foure thousand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> and yet since have I conferred with one that well knowes the place and profit of that Bishopricke, who affirms
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21149:8"/>that <hi>Spalato</hi> might have cut off from his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count three thousand &amp; eight hundred pounds of his former reckoning. He reported he heard with great delight and content one of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of <hi>Windsor</hi> preaching before the Kings Majesty, maintaine, that there was no cause why every man might not turne himselfe unto his Angell keeper, and say, <hi>Holy Angell keeper pray for me,</hi> avowing that ridiculous Romane do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practise of <hi>praying unto Saints and Angels in time of need:</hi> which was as false an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posture as this lying Impostor; who professeth to have heard that which he could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. The Sermon was in <hi>English,</hi> and he igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that language; as much unskild in it as in <hi>Irish</hi> or the <hi>Virginian Mattoakan</hi> tongue, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>carptim &amp; sparsim,</hi> it may be now and then, here and there a word. Lastly, this idle Lozell would undertake Reconciliation betwixt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant and Papist, Rome and England; whereas <hi>what agreement</hi> hath the Temple of God with Idols? what peace can be had with wicked Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busites, prophane Gibeonites, idolatrous Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, who have no peace with God? But these and many his like fabulous figments, which I could name, were nothing else but the very froth and foame of pride, which is said to be the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21149:9"/>
                  <hi>Tympanie of the soule:</hi> Now it was observed by divers, that this Monster of men did swell, and was puffed up no lesse in heart and minde, than he was in bodie.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>qu.</hi> 63. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note>
                  <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> hath obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that howsoever all sinne may be said to be in the Devill, <hi>secundum reatum;</hi> yet onely pride and envie is in him <hi>secundum affectum:</hi> and so though this titular Bishop were guiltie (as is well knowne) of many other capitall sinnes, yet this one only of pride came so neere his soule, that it stirred up almost all the rest. <hi>Vna superbia excitat omnia.</hi> But alas, <hi>(Pride going before destruction)</hi> his high aspiring thoughts have since bred his ruine; he being now <hi>miserorum miserrimus,</hi> lower than the lowest, as I shall hereafter shew.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This miscreant as he was guiltie of Pride and lying, so likewise of <hi>Slander</hi> and <hi>Irreligion. Slāder</hi> is <hi>Denigratio alienae famae,</hi> the smutting of a mans good name, or the wounding a man in his good name by a false report. As flatterie dawbes white upon blacke, so slander sprinkles blacke upon white. This SPALATO was observed to have beene of a very envious detracting minde. Had any learned man of our kingdome discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with him, and began to sift and sound of what spirit he was of (there being indeed alwaies great cause of jealousie) hee would smite them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21149:9"/>with the weapon of his tongue, and presently grow into passion, and say, That such a one were <hi>obesae naris, nullis disciplinarum ornamentis cumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, parum eruditus,</hi> with many the like keene and cutting reproaches. Soone after his comming into <hi>England,</hi> he made a voyage to the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> where hee was received with much honour and respect; his conversion gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulated with the tongues and phrases of the most elegant perpolite Orators of that famous Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demie, saluted with the Stentorian voice and noise of <hi>Doctors;</hi> his great, greazie, filthie, fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie paunch cheered with the daintiest cates the time could afford: yet after this nastie lubber his departure, he shamed not to report, that the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversitie knew not (forsooth) how to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine such a worthy Gentleman as he was: hee spake disgracefully of their Act, unworthily of those reverend Doctors, who as farre exceeded him for learning, as a burning Torch outshineth a little candle, or the light of true fire, excelleth any false, foggie, vaporous <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. As for Religion, I thinke hee had never any in him: For one that lived in the house with him, and tooke speciall notice of his actions, reported that he knew not him goe privately to his devotions in a halfe yeere together; but said
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21149:10"/>he would often sweare and curse fearefully: one of his oathes was, <hi>The pretious bloud of God poison me,</hi> as an <hi>Italian,</hi> who was often in companie with him, told me: And <hi>Let me never see Christ Iesus</hi> (he would say) if such a thing be not true, when oftentimes it was most false and untrue. And before his departure,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.13.</note> being <hi>come to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundnesse of iniquity,</hi> he would familiarly speake <hi>Blasphemie.</hi> Oh impious, irreligious wretch! How hath <hi>thy mouth abounded with evill,</hi> and <hi>thy tongue contrived fraud? Sitting thou didst speake against thy brother,</hi> and <hi>didst give scandall to the sonne of thy mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But I must here likewise accuse him, and that justly, for a <hi>luxurious Glutton:</hi> His <hi>Guet</hi> I must needs say was a <hi>Gulfe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Laert. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Diog.</note>
                  <hi>Charybdis,</hi> as <hi>Diogenes</hi> upon the like occasion spake very aptly. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> used daily to sacrifice to their <hi>Bell,</hi> he to his <hi>Belly, making it his god,</hi> Philip. 3.19. and his lungs the <hi>Temple,</hi> his paunch the <hi>Altar.</hi> Oh brutish Sacrificer. I could here speake much of this <hi>Belly-god;</hi> that he would often drinke <hi>usque ad ebrietatem,</hi> till hee were drunken. So that I cannot better compare him than unto a furnace, whose mouth is <hi>Gluttony,</hi> whose flame <hi>Pride,</hi> whose steame <hi>Luxurie,</hi> the sparkles <hi>filthy words,</hi> the smoake an <hi>evill name,</hi> the ashes have beene
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21149:10"/>
                  <hi>Povertie,</hi> and the end of all, <hi>Shame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Lastly, the end of him was a most <hi>perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Apostate.</hi> Apostasie is of three kinds, <hi>Perfidiae, Inobedientiae, Irregularitatis,</hi> of Misbeleefe, of Disobedience, of Irregularitie. Whether with <hi>Iulian</hi> he were guiltie of the former I know not, but I must and may not without cause accuse him of the two latter. He read the <hi>Articles</hi> of 1562. in <hi>West-Ilsly Church</hi> in <hi>Bark-shire,</hi> upon his <hi>Induction</hi> to that <hi>Benefice,</hi> and in the presence of divers witnesses <hi>subscribed</hi> to them: Since he professeth that he did it against his conscience (as also the taking of the oathes of Alleageance and Supremacie) the more dishonest, lewd, perjured knave he. Belike he thought still to make use of his Iesuited trickes of <hi>Equivocation, Collusion, Mentall Reservation,</hi> &amp;c. he having beene once a member of that Societie; and as himselfe repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he read <hi>Mathematickes, Rhetorick, Logick,</hi> and <hi>Philosophie</hi> to them, preached often amongst them, and did other domesticall service, for the which they were very sorie to leave him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21149:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shewing how this</hi> Dalmatian <hi>Mountebancke,</hi> M. ANTHONY, <hi>came to be fully discovered by the practise of the</hi> L. Gundamar, <hi>Embassadour from the King of</hi> Spaine.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is an old saying, <hi>Proditoris proditor,</hi> one knave most commonly will finde out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Birds of a feather doe not not alwaies flie together, but <hi>Aegyptians</hi> will be set against <hi>Aegyptians; Moechus contra Moechum, Latro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra latronem,</hi> a theefe against a theefe, a destroyer against a destroyer, a drunkard against a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, one Mountebanke against another. Right so it fared with <hi>Spalato</hi> and <hi>Gundamar,</hi> they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies fought one against another, yet not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies after the same manner: Sometimes they warred <hi>openly,</hi> sometimes covert and <hi>secretly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One while <hi>Gundamar</hi> shoots at <hi>Spalato</hi> with the great Canon of <hi>Irregularitie</hi> and <hi>Degradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> saying, that the <hi>Popes Holinesse</hi> had senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Bishop for foure notorious and capitall Crimes, to wit, Incest, Simonie, Drunkennesse and Bloud-shed, <hi>Grandia quidem peccata.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21149:11"/>
               <p>First, he accused him for having had three ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stards with his sisters daughter; a businesse that might well make him (if any thing) inegular.</p>
               <p>Secondly, hee charged him for Simoniacally attaining to, and leaving his two Bishoprickes of <hi>Segnia</hi> and <hi>Spalato.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, he vrged against him, that the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men in <hi>Segnia, Dalmatia,</hi> and the Citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> had all written unto his <hi>Holinesse,</hi> that he was very scandalous, in regard of company kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and usuall drunkennesse.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, he accused him for a most bloudie treacherie against the <hi>Isocchi,</hi> many of whom the <hi>Venetians</hi> by his meanes slew.</p>
               <p>The whole Information delivered under the <hi>L. Gundamars</hi> hand, translated into <hi>English,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>GVNDAMARS <hi>Jnformation against</hi> SPALATO.</head>
                  <p>AForlorne fellow there is of late come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> one MAR. ANTHONIVS <hi>de Dominis,</hi> who being adjudged by his brethren worthy to suffer death and to be burnt, suddenly and secretly fled to <hi>Venice,</hi> where hee was impiously and unjustly protected. This said
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21149:12"/>MARC. ANTHONIVS was first one of the <hi>Order of the Societie of Iesus,</hi> the most absolute <hi>Order</hi> of all others the Iudgements of God have beene many and wonderfull upon those that have Wrought themselves out of their <hi>Company,</hi> and yet this Societie may fitly becompared unto the <hi>Sea,</hi> that casteth forth the dead bodies, or to a <hi>vessell of new wine,</hi> which purgeth all the trash and corrupt matter which is mingled with it, and therefore they easily permit such as are not fit for them (such as <hi>Mar. Anthon. de Dominis</hi>) to depart from them, lest by staying amongst them, being stopt up like corruption close with the pure wine, they should breake the vessell wherein they are inclosed. <hi>Marcus Anthonius</hi> was not more willing to leave them, then they of the <hi>Societie of Iesus</hi> desirous to be rid of him. For Hee having vowed Obedience and Povertie, did notwithstanding aspire to a Bishoprick, and by <hi>Simony</hi> he at length attained to the Bishoprick of <hi>Segnia.</hi> You shall therefore understand that <hi>Segnia</hi> is a little Citie, but most impregnable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the confines of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whereof (commonly called <hi>Isocchi</hi>) doe neither plow nor plant for their sustenance, nor card nor spin for their clothing, nor trade with other Nations by way of merchandize, but live
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21149:12"/>altogether vpon spoile, either of the <hi>Turks,</hi> which is their profession, or else of <hi>Christians,</hi> when they please to mistake the one for the other. In which respect it is easier to finde those that would refuse (if they were either wise or honest) then such as would willingly accept the Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall government of this Ecclesiastical people. But howsoever <hi>Marc. Anthonius de Dominis</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not so he might but get the windie title of a Bishop, how he came to it, or what it cost him.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore the Bishop of <hi>Segnia</hi> being slaine in some enterprise of warre, amongst certaine souldiers of the Emperour, with whom hee was in company, <hi>Marcus Anthonius de Dominis,</hi> who was then a Iesuite in profession, though not in purpose, but desirous to be at libertie, forged let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the friends and kindred of the late Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop to himselfe, as to their kinsman, (which he was not) signifying, that the Bishop was not slaine, but taken prisoner, and intreating him to come to <hi>Segnia,</hi> from whence he might worke some meanes to set him at libertie. Vpon the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of which letters, his Superiours being willing enough to be rid of him, gave him leave to goe thither; where first hee obtained to supply the place of the late deceased Bishop, and afterwards by a great summe of money which he stole from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21149:13"/>the Iesuits, he came to be made Bishop himselfe. Which Episcopall function, as hee got by Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Forgerie, and Apostasie from his owne Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; so he behaved himselfe accordingly in the Administration thereof. For he carried with him to <hi>Segnia</hi> his Sisters daughter, by whom, within short time, he had no lesse than three bastards: he became a pot-companion with them of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and in bowsing and gormandizing was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing behinde any of them. Being then their Pastour and spirituall Father, he defrauded them of foure or five hundred crownes, which he got from them, under pretence of building a Quire in their Church, but converted the money to his owne use. And taking occasion to goe to <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> hee wrote backe to the <hi>Isocchi,</hi> his ghostly children, that he had made their peace with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and that they might safely faile in the <hi>Venetian Seas:</hi> vpon which assurance fortie of them sailing towards <hi>Turkie,</hi> were intrapped and slaine by the <hi>Venetian</hi> souldiers, at a certaine <hi>Iland,</hi> where they fell into the Snare, which their <hi>Reverend Father in God</hi> had laid for them. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of this his service to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> the Church of <hi>Spalato</hi> was gotten for him by the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> though it cost thē deare in some respects. This said Bishoprick was but poore in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21149:13"/>revenewes, worth but about some two hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> yet in respect of the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan dignitie, was fit to satisfie his ambition. This Bishoprick he kept but a little while, till he Simoniacally parted with it againe for a great summe of money, to a kinsman of his; having had some intelligence that <hi>His Holinesse</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> would proceed against him for his lewd life, and degrade him, which accordingly was done; and if the <hi>Venetians</hi> had not protected him, hee had tasted of the fire according to his desert. This wicked wretch is since come into <hi>England,</hi> where hee will ere long begin to shew himselfe in the same colours as hee did at <hi>Segnia, Spalato,</hi> and <hi>Venice.</hi> In the meane while he will serve for a wonder to be shewed up and downe the streets for fooles and children to looke on.</p>
                  <p>Here was one volley of shot discharged against <hi>Spalato</hi> in this Information of the L. <hi>Gundamar.</hi> With many other horrid and horrible enormities did the L. <hi>Gundamar,</hi> opēly in every place where he came, charge the new-arrived, much admired <hi>Spalato.</hi> Yet all this was supposed to be nothing else but <hi>Iniquorum individua comes calumnia,</hi> the idle ejaculations of Envie and detraction; and therefore <hi>Gundamars</hi> word proved hitherto no <hi>Slander,</hi> though hee laid on load boldly: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21149:14"/>was beleeved that only the relinquishment of <hi>Romish</hi> Idolatrous impietie had gained the <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matian</hi> Bishop all these Reproaches.</p>
                  <p>But as he that layeth siege to a Citie, when he findeth that one stratagem will not availe his Invasion, presently deviseth another, or percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that open hostilitie will purchase him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing presently, practiseth secret suffocation. So fared it with L. <hi>Gundamar</hi> (a shrewd Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villian) when one assault could not a vaile him, he presently putteth in practise another: when Martiall belligerating thundring Invectives ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the turne, forth with hee falles to secret undermining, and then acted his part, displayed his colours in manner following.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eight (who Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Spalato</hi>) being dead, Simonaically succeeded him <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, who in former times had beene of <hi>Spalato's</hi> familiar acquaintance, and from whom he might hope for extraordinarie favour and preferment if he should returne to <hi>Rome. Gundamar</hi> full of diabolicall craft and policie, thought he might best worke upon this advantage, saying to himselfe, (as did sometimes another his Satanicall brother) <hi>Plus lingua quam gladius,</hi> my tongue shall at length conquer, where my sword could not; and so comes to <hi>Spalato,</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21149:14"/>and telles him, that though some unkindnesse had passed betweene them, yet at length hee would be his friend, and was sorie, consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Learning and uncomparable deserving hee should live here in <hi>England,</hi> where bee as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured him hee was much maligned, and used but as a Stale, hereafter to publish store of books in his name. He said hee would undertake hee should be made a Cardinall upon his returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his owne Countrey, where many his friends bemoaned him, and <hi>Paul,</hi> the then Pope, would thinke it a great happinesse to see him. For saith hee) I can shew you a letter lately come to my hands from his <hi>Holinesse,</hi> who writes unto mee, desiring to be certified what is become of you, and if I speake with you, to signifie how much he desires your Good, and that hee will excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly further your preferment, if you shal come unto him; and for <hi>Gundamar</hi> drawes out of his pocket the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ded Letter sent him from the Pope, and bids him reade it; which containing many sugred promises of preferment, if <hi>Spalato</hi> should come to him to <hi>Rome:</hi> the Sun-shine thereof presently dazeled his eies, and the titular <hi>Dalmatian</hi> Bishop, who before like another <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan</hi> would drinke up <hi>Iordan,</hi> and overthrow the Popes Supremacie, now presently promiseth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21149:15"/>to joine forces with him: and told the L. <hi>Gunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> that if he meant well toward him, he would returne ho me to <hi>Rome. Gundamar</hi> all this while, like a craftie <hi>Hiaena,</hi> though he spake like a <hi>friend,</hi> devoured like a <hi>soe,</hi> and like <hi>Ioab the Captaine of the Hoast,</hi> though he spake kindly to <hi>Amasa,</hi> and kissed him, yet presently stabbed him; like the <hi>Harpie,</hi> though he carried a faire Virgin face, yet he had <hi>Vultures</hi> tallons. His plot was to bring him in disgrace here in <hi>England,</hi> and then to pack him over to <hi>Rome</hi> in a cloake-bag, where hee might live neere the fresh aire of the <hi>Inquisition.</hi> So that here was a dangerous Rocke hid under a calme sea, the <hi>Syrens</hi> song became the <hi>Sailours</hi> wreck, the Fowlers whistle was the birds death, a hidden bait was the great <hi>Dalmatian</hi> fish his bane.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gundamar,</hi> that he might yet better unmaske this titular Bishop (who had all this while stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked up and downe in our Kingdome, with the visard of Hypocrisie on his face) caused him to write a letter to the <hi>Pope</hi> intimating his resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to leave <hi>England,</hi> and come to <hi>Rome,</hi> which accordingly <hi>Spalato</hi> did; and no sooner had hee delivered his letter to <hi>Gundamar,</hi> to be sent to <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>Gundamar</hi> shewed the same to such of our kingdome as he thought fit the same should
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21149:15"/>be discovered unto. Thus it happened <hi>Episcopo tepido,</hi> to this luke-warme Bishop; and thus, (as I told you before) <hi>Proditoris proditor,</hi> one craftie Impostor laid open the other.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shewing how that</hi> SPALATO <hi>being discovered, he desired leave of his Majestie to returne into</hi> Italy, <hi>upon pretence to reforme and reunite the Christian world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe titular <hi>Dalmatian Bishop,</hi> M. ANTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIVS <hi>de Dominis,</hi> after his abode in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> some three or foure yeeres, though much suspected, was not yet fully detected, till by his aforesaid friend, the L. <hi>Gundamar,</hi> who warily laying his bait, soone caught and intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him like a Salmon in a net, which he would have broken thorow, but wanted might and sleight. Perceiving at length how hee was cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented, he went unto his <hi>Majestie,</hi> desiring leave to returne unto his owne country, assuring him hee was the same in minde, opinion, and judgement, as he professed himselfe to be at his first arrivall in <hi>England.</hi> His Majestie, <hi>prudenti
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21149:16"/>pectore &amp; rerum usu longê maximus,</hi> being assured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly most wise, and knowing how to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in this businesse, without any <hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> complement of inviting him to an Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, gave him leave, so soone as he pleased, to be gone; and finding his levitie, was willing to be quit and freed of him; yet asked him what occasioned his so sudden desire of departure, and how he durst (if not altered in opinion) trust unreconcileable <hi>Rome,</hi> (his Majestie in truth plainly perceiving what would be the end of him.)</p>
               <p>SPALATO his answer was thus, That no unbridled affection, no temporall necessitie, no strange event, nor grievous mischance did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell him to depart, but for that the then Pope was his former acquaintance &amp; friend, he feared not the <hi>Ignatian</hi> furie, but would venture to visit <hi>Rome,</hi> or the <hi>Italian</hi> adjacent parts; his project being sage and considerate, his designement of no ordinarie consequent, but of this nature as followeth, <hi>viz. That he meant to reconcile and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite the Christian world,</hi> which hee was sure hee could performe, having had a naturall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne desire of Vnitie from his Infancie: <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culeum opus;</hi> sure a hard taske. This <hi>Spirit</hi> of his being so contrary to the Spirit of the Church, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21149:16"/>the Spirit of Christ himselfe, and in fine contrary to the very light of reason and humane un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding. What union and conjunction can there be of the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West, North</hi> and <hi>South?</hi> Our Mother <hi>Eve,</hi> out of a vaine curiositie,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.2.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring with the Serpent, whom shee might thinke to be an Angell, fell into Heresie; but this man out of a curiositie more than mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.3.5.</note> would perswade <hi>the sheepe of Christ to heare the voice of a stranger,</hi> and to conferre with that Serpent of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom in his bookes hee said he knew and confessed to be the Deuill: But it appeareth sufficiently that hee hath not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed those rules of <hi>discerning spirits,</hi> which with a little humility he might have learned in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For the <hi>Spirit</hi> which giveth true faith, is the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>humilitie;</hi> which is testified by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3. The spirit of Pride, is the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Heresie. The Fairie which led away the <hi>Dalmatian</hi> Bishop, was the spirit of Pride, which made him undertake that taske which is too hard for him, or for any the wisest man this day alive. But according to <hi>S. Bernard, Multi stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent plus alta, quam aptaproferre.</hi> The Wise-man therefore gives this counsell unto those fooles, whose curiositie transports their spirits after needlesse and unprofitable Inquisition: <hi>Altiora
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21149:17"/>te ne quaesieris, &amp; fortiora te ne scruteris.</hi> Seeke not for things that are too high for thee, nor search after things that are too mightie. <hi>Many</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</note> and it may well be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the <hi>Dalmatian</hi> Bishop) <hi>will be the Doctors of the Law, neither understanding what they say, nor whereof they affirme.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fulbert. Carnoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis epist.</hi> 1.</note> In which sense, true is that of <hi>Fulbertus Carnotensis,</hi> that <hi>while they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to become disciples, or schollers of the truth, they make themselves the Masters of errour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shewing what entertainment</hi> MARCVS AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TONIVS de Dominis, <hi>the nominall Bishop of</hi> Spalato <hi>found upon his late returne to</hi> Rome.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SPALATO being on his journey betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> was so gogged with assured hopes of what supereminent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment hee should have conferred on him by his old acquaintance, the <hi>Pope,</hi> upon his arrivall to <hi>Rome,</hi> that lower than a <hi>Cardinall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> his aspiring thoughts could not or would not descend. But according to <hi>Aristotles</hi> rule, <hi>Frustra est illa potentia quae non reducitur ad actum,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21149:17"/>Vaine is that hope which endeth in nothing.
<q>
                     <l>Oft over-bold Ambition fires her nest,</l>
                     <l>And burnes her wings with shame, or ends in jest.</l>
                  </q> Whilest the tide of this <hi>Bishops Ambition</hi> carried him head-long into an Ocean of hoped prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hee suddenly became drowned in a verie gulfe of distresse. For as hee was about to land, and set footing within the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> he was received into a close Cell neere the Church of <hi>S. Laurence</hi> without <hi>Porta Esquilina:</hi> And there continued fourteene daies without receiving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny message at all from his <hi>Holinesse.</hi> A cold wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it was; but this was done to ease his heart after so tedious a journey. If hee had presently come amongst his old acquaintance, their many greetings might have done as much hurt as his trauailes.</p>
               <p>After this he was sent to a cloister within the Church of <hi>S. Sebastian</hi> and <hi>Fabian,</hi> where there was appointed to attend on him for a weeke a <hi>Confessor,</hi> and he had certaine Articles delivered him, which he was advised to consider of, and to subscribe to them within three daies follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Then was sent unto him from his <hi>Holinesse</hi> the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Ancona,</hi> who was appointed to conferre with him about his voyage into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and to signifie unto the <hi>Pope</hi> his sorrow
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21149:18"/>and repentance for the same. This Bishop became his great friend, and soone after got leave of the <hi>Pope</hi> that <hi>Spalato</hi> himselfe might have accesse to him, and conferre with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spalato</hi> being brought before the <hi>Pope,</hi> was not whispered in the eare with another Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprick or Cardinall-ship, as hee expected, but advised by his <hi>Holinesse</hi> to make his peace with God and the Church, and then he should finde all lawfull favour at his hands. And so the <hi>Pope</hi> commanded him for a time to live a retired con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative life in one of the Monasteries of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there betake himselfe to some Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious order. Accordingly, like a brute beast or Swine they shut him up in a stye, and immured him within the walles of a Cloister, neere the Church of <hi>S. Iohn de Lateran,</hi> and injoyned him, as part of his penance, to write a booke, wherein to give satisfaction for his former Apostasie and Revolt from them. Accordingly he performed his taske, and his spurious Pamphlet hath (I am sure) beene seene and read by divers in our Kingdome: wherein, without all modestie, he belieth our Church in generall, which he hath often publikely and privately commended and admired; and like a very loose Lozell, he cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lessely complaineth of divers of most eminent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21149:18"/>place in our kingdome. Lastly, without wit or judgement, he bringeth a many base Invectives bumbasted out with foaming malice against himselfe: And hee graspeth together such an heape of confused matter, spun out and patched together in a company of darke sentences, that it will dazle any mans understanding to heare or reade it. For my part I had compassion of the poore mans simplicitie, when I beheld his book fraught with so many disadvantages against himselfe, wherein without further helpe he hath overthrowne that phantasticall tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> which before he was a building: and no neerer is he to the knowledge of the truth, from which he is fallen by his revolt from our Church, than the fall of <hi>Lucifer</hi> could end in heaven.</p>
               <p>Besides the <hi>Penance</hi> injoined him, of writing his said selfe-accusing-condemning booke, hee hath since endured many mortifying passions, flagellant diseases which terminated in a mortall incurable consumption, he having (as is suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed) of late breathed his last in the Castle of <hi>Saint Angelo,</hi> neere the <hi>Popes</hi> Palace of <hi>S. Peters,</hi> where he found the case strangely altered, in regard of what his friend, the L. <hi>Gundamar,</hi> promised him here in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21149:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shewing the manner of the titular Arch-bishop of</hi> Spalato <hi>his commitment to the Castle of</hi> S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo <hi>within the precincts of</hi> Rome, <hi>and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of his said imprisonment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Could here expresse a whole <hi>Iliad</hi> of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that attended the <hi>Arch-bishop</hi> of <hi>Spalato</hi> upon his comming to <hi>Rome, Mala malis suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentia &amp; agminatim ingruentia,</hi> One evill trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon the heeles of another; <hi>Et dum adve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit vnum non advenit solum.</hi> But of all terribles, the most terrible was his Commitment to the Castle of <hi>S. Angelo,</hi> (a place somewhat worse than the <hi>Inquisition</hi>) of which it may be said in some sort, as of the Lions den.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Multi te adversum spectantes, nemo retrorsum:</hi> Of those that are committed to this said Castle, few or none ever after see the sun-shine. They have an old saying in the Northerne parts of <hi>England,</hi> which is this, <hi>From Hell, Hull, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifax, good Lord deliver us;</hi> but at <hi>Rome</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon saying is, <hi>From the Tower in Saint Angelo save us good Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21149:19"/>
               <p>The <hi>Romanists</hi> speake much of their fained dreamed <hi>Purgatory,</hi> but where the place thereof is, none of their Purgatory Rakers or Proctors is able to declare: But I beleeve if there be any Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie any where, it is in the vault of the Castle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> which hath swallowed up many a man, who shall never be more heard of untill the day of Doome. This vault is reported to be twelvescore yards in depth, and into it are tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled many men alive; there being a roome over it which hath a trap-doore or drawing floore: the person condemned to be throwne into this Purgatorian Vault, hath prepared for him, in the roome over, a kinde of little cage or boxe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he is shut, and in which he may hardly turne him. Being once put into this coope, hee hath a Confessor that comes to him some halfe dozen times, and then when he little suspects or dreames of it, the forged floore or trap-doore is let downe by a device which they have, and then downe tumbles the poore prisoner into this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most on plummettable hole or gulfe; the boxe into which hee was shut remaining his coffin. And of the time when the condemned is thus let fall, none of his friends ever know, nor once heare of, but yet are assured that <hi>ab eo Purgatorio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> est redemptio,</hi> from that not fiery, false and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21149:20"/>fained, but truly reall Purgatorie there is indeed no redemption; and therefore I conclude, <hi>istinc ut ab inferno libera nos Domine,</hi> from hell and thence good Lord deliver us. The <hi>Dalmatian Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop</hi> hath (as some say) alreadie had his penance there: His perswaded assured hopes ended in a personall censure, to sinke in that bottomlesse, breathlesse Vault or Gulfe.</p>
               <p>Yet within these few daies have I seene cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine letters from <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein was signified, that the <hi>Archbishop</hi> of <hi>Spalato</hi> hath had (since his former censure) another sentence pronounced against him, which hath beene put in execution, <hi>viz.</hi> to frie in the <hi>fire,</hi> and to be <hi>burnt</hi> flesh and bones to cinders, in the sight of many thousands of people.</p>
               <p>The reasons of which condemnation and sufferings of his, were these that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Spalato</hi> having beene for the space of a yeere shut up in a Monastery at <hi>Rome,</hi> petitioned unto the present Pope to have his enlargement, and for his health sake desired to travell to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> But the Pope perceiving how willing hee was to slip coller, and be ranging after his old guise and fashion, by no meanes would yeeld unto his said request, but became jealous of him. Whereupon <hi>Spalato</hi> full of discontent, uttered
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21149:20"/>words against the discipline of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> preferring the discipline and gouernment of the Reformed Churches, farre before that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholike Chaire. This newes came to the <hi>Holy Father</hi> the Popes eares.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then the Pope sent unto <hi>Spalato, Pater Lodozasques,</hi> to demand of him when he would give satisfaction to the Church for the bookes that he wrote in <hi>England,</hi> in which he accused his Mother, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for a verie Strumpet or Harlot. <hi>Spalato</hi> replied that he grew ill and sickly, and was altogether unfit, in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, to undertake such an hard taske, as to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer those great Volumes of his own, except the Pope would give him leave to travell to a better aire than that of <hi>Rome,</hi> (which belike was too neere the Inquisition, which he doubted would at length stiffle him, except hee could by some wile get further from it.)</p>
               <p n="3">3. Vpon these passages and answers of his, the <hi>Pope</hi> &amp; Conclave of <hi>Rome</hi> resolved they would soone sift &amp; finde out <hi>Spalato's</hi> meaning, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the premises. To which end they cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly plotted and practised with one <hi>Camelo,</hi> a Monke, who had beene with <hi>Spalato</hi> here in <hi>England.</hi> They so tempered and wrought with this said <hi>Camelo,</hi> that he soone betrayed his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21149:21"/>
                  <hi>Spalato</hi> unto them, which he performed in this manner.</p>
               <p>First, he discovered unto them certaine <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> doctrines, which <hi>Spalato</hi> persisted to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
               <p>Secondly, hee got from <hi>Spalato</hi> certaine pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of his, lately written with his owne hand since his comming from <hi>England,</hi> in which he seemed, like a lustie stout valiant Pugill, by argument to maintaine his former <hi>Lutheran</hi> quarrell.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Camelo</hi> declared that <hi>Spalato</hi> had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten plotted an escape from <hi>Rome,</hi> and had told him, there could be no safetie for him so long as he continued so neere the Popes nose.</p>
               <p>These businesses thus informed against <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lato,</hi> wrought his destruction, and without more adoe, was upon the six and twentieth day of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary last committed to the Castle of Saint <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo,</hi> where he remained till the day that he was brought unto the stake to bee burned. Where, if his last end were no better than his former course and trade of life; he might well curse <hi>the wombe that bare him, and the pappes that gave him sucke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely the infamous shipwracke wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hee fell, first of all <hi>Vertue,</hi> which is the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21149:21"/>and secondly of <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the ship of eternall life; and lastly of all good name and common honestie (without the which this present life is far worse than any temporal death) hath made him a perpetuall and a most dreadfull example for all honest men, to take heed how they dally with God almightie, and be but luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme Gospellers, was this miserable titular Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop at the best was. Againe, let men beware of Ambition, which was the morsell that choaked him, when he might have fared otherwise well enough here in <hi>England.</hi> Lastly, let every good Christian above all things care to keepe a good conscience, which hee neglecting, made ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of his faith, and was therefore given o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by Almightie God unto impenitencie and hardnesse of heart, to heape or store up wrath to himselfe against the day of wrath, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the weight of his own damnation, against the time of the revelation of Gods just judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who shall render unto every man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes.</p>
               <p>Though this be a world of shadowes, a thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of disguises, a map of colours, a shop of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, a schoole of hypocrisie: yet a time will come when in the court of heaven, all maskes shall be put off, save the veile of righteousnesse,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21149:22"/>no <hi>sucus</hi> shall stay on, but the tincture of Christs bloud, no habit shall be in fashion, but a robe of Innocencie, no crafts-master shall get in, but a plaine Christian. And as for <hi>Rome,</hi> whosoever thou art, having separated thy selfe from her, maist yet be perswaded with <hi>Spalato,</hi> to returne unto her; assure thy selfe that it is most true which <hi>Theodoricus</hi> of <hi>Niem</hi> long since af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed of her, that she is a cruell Dame, unjust, impious, unreconcileable, to be compared with <hi>Nilus,</hi> which bred monsters, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:21149:22"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:21149:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:21149:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:21149:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>